like Pong, Snake and Tetris. You can imagine the tremendous joy of playing with a Tetris game that you wrote in JACK and then compiled into machine language in a compiler that you wrote also, and then seeing the result running on a machine that you built starting with nothing more than a few thousand NAND gates. It's a tremendous personal triumph of going from first principles all the way to a fantastically complex and useful system. Noam and I worked five years to facilitate this ascent and to create the tools and infrastructure that will enable students to build it in one semester. And this is the great team that helped us make it happen. The trick was to decompose the computer's construction into numerous stand-alone modules, each of which could be individually specified, built and unit-tested in isolation from the rest of the project. And from day one, Noam and I decided to put all these building blocks freely available in open source on the Web. So chip specifications, APIs, project descriptions, software tools, hardware simulators, CPU emulators, stacks of hundreds of slides, lectures -- we laid out everything on the Web and invited the world to come over, take whatever they need, and do whatever they want with it. And then something fascinating happened. The world came. And in short order, thousands of people were building our machine. And NAND2Tetris became one of the first massive, open, online courses, although seven years ago we had no idea that what we were doing is called MOOCs. We just observed how self-organized courses were kind of spontaneously spawning out of our materials. For example, Pramode C.E., an engineer from Kerala, India, has organized groups of self-learners who build our computer under his good guidance. And Parag Shah, another engineer, from Mumbai, has unbundled our projects into smaller, more manageable bites that he now serves in his pioneering do-it-yourself computer science program. The people who are attracted to these courses typically have a hacker mentality. They want to figure out how things work, and they want to do it in groups, like this hackers club in Washington, D.C., that uses our materials to offer community courses. And because these materials are widely available and open-source, different people take them to very different and unpredictable directions. For example, Yu Fangmin, from Guangzhou, has used FPGA technology to build our computer and show others how to do the same using a video clip, and Ben Craddock developed a very nice computer game that unfolds inside our CPU architecture, which is quite a complex 3D maze that Ben developed using the Minecraft 3D simulator engine. The Minecraft community went bananas over this project, and Ben became an instant media celebrity. And indeed, for quite a few people, taking this NAND2Tetris pilgrimage, if you will, has turned into a life-changing experience. For example, take Dan Rounds, who is a music and math major from East Lansing, Michigan. A few weeks ago, Dan posted a victorious post on our website, and I'd like to read it to you. So here's what Dan said. "I did the coursework because understanding computers is important to me, just like literacy and numeracy, and I made it through. I never worked harder on anything, never been challenged to this degree. But given what I now feel capable of doing, I would certainly do it again. To anyone considering NAND2Tetris, it's a tough journey, but you'll be profoundly changed." So Dan demonstrates the many self-learners who take this course off the Web, on their own traction, on their own initiative, and it's quite amazing because these people cannot care less about grades. They are doing it because of one motivation only. They have a tremendous passion to learn. And with that in mind, I'd like to say a few words about traditional college grading. I'm sick of it. We are obsessed with grades because we are obsessed with data, and yet grading takes away all the fun from failing, and a huge part of education is about failing. Courage, according to Churchill, is the ability to go from one defeat to another without losing enthusiasm. (Laughter) And [Joyce] said that mistakes are the portals of discovery. And yet we don't tolerate mistakes, and we worship grades. So we collect your B pluses and your A minuses and we aggregate them into a number like 3.4, which is stamped on your forehead and sums up who you are. Well, in my opinion, we went too far with this nonsense, and grading became degrading. So with that, I'd like to say a few words about upgrading, and share with you a glimpse from my current project, which is different from the previous one, but it shares exactly the same characteristics of self-learning, learning by doing, self-exploration and community-building, and this project deals with K-12 math education, beginning with early age math, and we do it on tablets because we believe that math, like anything else, should be taught hands on. So here's what we do. Basically, we developed numerous mobile apps, every one of them explaining a particular concept in math. So for example, let's take area. When you deal with a concept like area -- well, we also provide a set of tools that the child is invited to experiment with in order to learn. So if area is what interests us, then one thing which is natural to do is to tile the area of this particular shape and simply count how many tiles it takes to cover it completely. And this little exercise here gives you a first good insight of the notion of area. Moving along, what about the area of this figure? Well, if you try to tile it, it doesn't work too well, does it. So instead, you can experiment with these different tools here by some process of guided trial and error, and at some point you will discover that one thing that you can do among several legitimate transformations is the following one. You can cut the figure, you can rearrange the parts, you can glue them and then proceed to tile just like we did before. (Applause) Now this particular transformation did not change the area of the original figure, so a six-year-old who plays with this has just discovered a clever algorithm to compute the area of any given parallelogram. We don't replace teachers, by the way. We believe that teachers should be empowered, not replaced. Moving along, what about the area of a triangle? So after some guided trial and error, the child will discover, with or without help, that he or she can duplicate the original figure and then take the result, transpose it, glue it to the original and then proceed [with] what we did before: cut, rearrange, paste — oops— paste and glue, and tile. Now this transformation has doubled the area of the original figure, and therefore we have just learned that the area of the triangle equals the area of this rectangle divided by two. But we discovered it by self-exploration. So, in addition to learning some useful geometry, the child has been exposed to some pretty sophisticated science strategies, like reduction, which is the art of transforming a complex problem into a simple one, or generalization, which is at the heart of any scientific discipline, or the fact that some properties are invariant under some transformations. And all this is something that a very young child can pick up using such mobile apps. So presently, we are doing the following: First of all, we are decomposing the K-12 math curriculum into numerous such apps. And because we cannot do it on our own, we've developed a very fancy authoring tool that any author, any parent or actually anyone who has an interest in math education, can use this authoring tool to develop similar apps on tablets without programming. And finally, we are putting together an adaptive ecosystem that will match different learners with different apps according to their evolving learning style. The driving force behind this project is my colleague Shmulik London, and, you see, just like Salman did about 90 years ago, the trick is to surround yourself with brilliant people, because at the end, it's all about people. And a few years ago, I was walking in Tel Aviv and I saw this graffiti on a wall, and I found it so compelling that by now I preach it to my students, and I'd like to try to preach it to you. Now, I don't know how many people here are familiar with the term "mensch." It basically means to be human and to do the right thing. And with that, what this graffiti says is, "High-tech schmigh-tech. The most important thing is to be a mensch." (Laughter) Thank you. (Applause) (Applause)
como Pong, Snake y Tetris. Se imaginarán la enorme alegría de jugar con un Tetris que uno mismo escribió en JACK y luego compiló en lenguaje máquina en un compilador que también escribió, y luego ver el resultado ejecutando en una máquina que uno construyó partiendo de nada más que unos miles de compuertas NAND. Es un triunfo personal enorme partir de principios fundamentales para llegar a un sistema extremadamente complejo y útil. Noam y yo trabajamos cinco años para facilitar este ascenso y crear las herramientas y la infraestructura para que los estudiantes construyan esto en un semestre. Y este es el gran equipo que nos ayudó a realizarlo. El truco consistió en descomponer la construcción en muchos módulos independientes, que pudiesen especificarse de forma individual, y construirse y probarse de manera aislada del resto del proyecto. Desde el primer día, Noam y yo decidimos poner a disposición estos bloques libremente como código abierto en la Web. Dejamos especificaciones de chips, APIs, especificaciones del proyecto, simuladores de hardware, emuladores de CPU, pilas de cientos de diapositivas, conferencias... dejamos todo eso en la Web e invitamos al mundo a venir y tomar lo que necesitara y hacer lo que quisiera con esto. Y entonces ocurrió algo fascinante. El mundo vino. Y, en poco tiempo, miles de personas estaban construyendo nuestra máquina. Así, NAND2Tetris fue uno de los primeros cursos web abiertos y masivos, aunque hace siete años no teníamos ni idea de que eso en inglés se llamaba MOOC. Sólo notábamos cómo se desprendían cursos autoorganizados espontáneamente a partir de nuestros materiales. Por ejemplo, Pramode C.E., un ingeniero de Kerala, India, ha organizado grupos de autodidactas que construyen nuestra máquina bajo su buena dirección. Y Parag Shah, otro ingeniero, de Mumbai, desagregó nuestros proyectos en partes más pequeñas y manejables que ahora ofrece en su programa aficionado de ciencias de la computación. Las personas atraídas por estos cursos por lo general tienen mentalidad de 'hacker'. Quieren saber cómo funcionan las cosas, y quieren hacerlo en grupos, como este club de hackers en Washington, DC, que usa nuestros materiales en cursos comunitarios. Y como estos materiales están ampliamente disponibles y son de código abierto, las personas pueden cambiar el rumbo en direcciones imprevistas. Por ejemplo, Yu Fangmin, de Guangzhou, ha usado la tecnología FPGA para construir nuestra computadora y mostrarle a otros cómo hacer lo mismo mediante un video y Ben Craddock desarrolló un videojuego muy bonito en nuestra arquitectura de CPU, un laberinto 3D bastante complejo desarrollado por Ben con el simulador Minecraft 3D. La comunidad de Minecraft se volvió loca con este proyecto y Ben se convirtió en una celebridad mediática. Y, en efecto, para algunas personas emprender esta peregrinación del NAND2Tetris, si se quiere, se ha convertido en una experiencia que les cambió la vida. Por ejemplo, Dan Rounds, músico y especialista en matemática de East Lansing, Michigan. Hace pocas semanas, Dan publicó un mensaje victorioso en nuestro sitio, y me gustaría leérselo. Esto es lo que dijo Dan: "Hice el curso porque entender la computación es tan importante para mí como la alfabetización y la aritmética, y lo logré. Nunca antes había trabajado tan arduamente en algo, nunca antes enfrenté semejante desafío. Pero sabiendo como ahora sé de lo que soy capaz, sin duda lo volvería a hacer. Para quien esté considerando hacer NAND2Tetris, es un viaje difícil, pero te cambiará significativamente". Dan demostró que muchos autodidactas toman este curso desconectados, a su propio ritmo, por iniciativa propia, y es muy sorprendente porque a estas personas no podría importarles menos las calificaciones. Lo hacen motivados por una sola cosa. Sienten una enorme pasión por aprender. Y con eso en mente, me gustaría decir unas palabras sobre las calificaciones universitarias tradicionales. Estoy harto de ellas. Las calificaciones nos obsesionan, porque nos obsesionan los datos. Las calificaciones le quitan la diversión al fracaso, y la educación en gran medida consiste en fracasar. El valor, según Churchill, es la capacidad de ir de un fracaso a otro sin perder el entusiasmo. (Risas) Y [Joyce] dijo que los errores son los portales del descubrimiento. Y, sin embargo, no toleramos los errores y adoramos las calificaciones. Juntamos los regulares y los buenos y los consolidamos en un número como 3,4 que está estampado en tu frente y resume lo que eres. Bueno, en mi opinión, fuimos demasiado lejos con esta tontería y la calificación se tornó "des-calificación". Con eso, me gustaría decir unas palabras sobre la actualización, y compartir con Uds. una idea de mi proyecto actual, que es diferente del anterior, pero comparte las mismas características de aprender haciéndolo uno mismo, de la exploración personal y el desarrollo comunitario y abarca la educación inicial y primaria en matemáticas. Empieza con matemáticas a temprana edad y con tabletas porque creemos que la matemática, como todo, debe enseñarse con las manos en la masa. Por eso, en esencia, desarrollamos muchas aplicaciones móviles, cada una dedicada a un concepto matemático particular. Por ejemplo, tomemos "área". Cuando uno trabaja un concepto como área... bueno, siempre brindamos unas herramientas que invitan al chico a experimentar para aprender. Así, si lo que nos interesa es el área, lo que resulta natural es dividirla en piezas con esta forma y simplemente contar cuántas piezas se requieren para cubrir el área. Y este pequeño ejercicio da una buena idea preliminar del concepto de área. Continuando, ¿qué pasa con el área de esta figura? Bueno, si tratamos de cuadricularla eso no funciona bien, ¿no? En cambio, podemos experimentar con estas herramientas, siguiendo una guía, por ensayo y error, hasta que en un momento descubriremos que, entre las varias transformaciones legítimas, existe una en la que si cortamos la figura podemos reagrupar las partes, pegarlas, y luego cuadricular el área como hicimos antes. (Aplausos) Pero esta transformación particular no cambió el área de la figura original así que niñas y niños de 6 años que juegan con esto han descubierto un algoritmo ingenioso para calcular el área de cualquier paralelogramo. No reemplazamos a los maestros, por cierto. Creemos en facultar a los maestros, no en reemplazarlos. Siguiendo, ¿qué pasa con el área del triángulo? Luego de un ensayo y error dirigido se descubre, con o sin ayuda, que se puede duplicar la figura original para luego transponerla, pegarla a la figura original y después proceder como hicimos antes: cortamos, reagrupamos, pegamos — uy— pegamos y cuadriculamos. Pero esta transformación ha duplicado el área de la figura original, y por lo tanto acabamos de aprender que el área del triángulo equivale al área de este rectángulo dividido por dos. Lo descubrimos mediante autoexploración. Así, además de aprender algo útil de geometría se aprenden estrategias científicas bastante sofisticadas como la reducción que es el arte de transformar un problema complejo en uno simple, o la generalización que es el centro de cualquier disciplina científica, o el hecho de que algunas propiedades son invariables bajo ciertas transformaciones. Y todo esto es algo que los pequeños pueden aprender con sus aplicaciones móviles. Actualmente, hacemos lo siguiente. Primero, descomponemos el plan de estudios de matemática inicial y primaria en muchas de estas aplicaciones. Y, como no podemos hacerlo por nuestra cuenta, hemos desarrollado una herramienta muy elegante que cualquier autor, padre o, de hecho cualquier persona interesada en enseñar matemática, puede usar esta herramienta para desarrollar aplicaciones similares en tabletas, sin programación. Y, por último, estamos armando un ecosistema adaptativo que se ajustará a diferentes alumnos con aplicaciones diferentes de acuerdo a su evolución en el aprendizaje. La fuerza subyacente que impulsa este proyecto es mi colega Shmulik London, y, ya ven, igual que hizo Salman hace unos 90 años, el truco es rodearse de personas brillantes, porque al final, en todo están las personas. Hace unos años caminaba por Tel Aviv, vi este graffiti en una pared y me pareció tan convincente que ahora lo predico a mis estudiantes, y me gustaría hacerlo con Uds. No sé cuántos de los aquí presentes están familiarizados con el término "Mensch". Básicamente significa "ser humano" y hacer lo correcto. Dicho esto, este graffiti dice: "Alta tecnología, tecnología 'schmigh'. Lo más importante es ser un 'Mensch'". (Risas) Gracias. (Aplausos) (Aplausos)